Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Edward G. Wilson Papers, 1906-1991, bulk 1946-1971 RL.00758
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Edward G. Wilson papers
1906-1991, bulk 1946-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00758
43 Linear Feet
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Edward G. Wilson was an executive with JWT from 1930 until his retirement in 1971, and held the positions of General Counsel, Executive Vice-President and Secretary of the Company. The Edward G. Wilson Papers span the period 1906-1991 and includes clippings, correspondence, inter-office memoranda, reports, writings, speeches and personal diaries that highlight Wilson's 40 year career (1930-1971) as an executive with the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT). The bulk of materials fall between 1946 and 1971, and covers the period from Wilson's return to JWT following military service in World War II until his retirement. As General Counsel and head of JWT's Legal Department, Wilson oversaw contractual relations pertaining primarily to the sponsorship of radio and television programs for a number of clients--including DeBeers Consolidated Mines, Ltd., the Eastman Kodak Company, the Ford Motor Company, the Scott Paper Company and Unilever. The collection reveals JWT's relationships with radio and television personalities--such as Fred Allen and Edgar Bergen--and professional organizations including the Radio Writers Guild and the Television Writers of America. In addition, materials in the collection touch on the anti-communist movement and blacklisting within the U.S. entertainment industry of the 1950s--involving personalities such as Jean Muir and John Henry Faulk, among others. The collection also includes records from a number of JWT international offices, with heavier representation from offices in London; Bombay (Mumbai), India; and Johannesburg, South Africa, along with records kept by some of Wilson's predecessors, such as Donald Foote and Sam Meek, and the South African advertising executive and politician James Hamilton Russell.
30,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Sensitive personnel materials pertaining to individual employment are closed to non-JWT users for 75 years from the date of the file creation.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Edward G. Wilson Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1987.
Biographical and Historical Note
Chronology
1909 Mar. 23 Born Edward George Wilson, Richmond, Ind.
1930 Received AB Degree, Earlham College, Richmond, Ind.
1930 Joined J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), Treasurer's Office
1934 Received JD from New York University Law School, New York, N.Y.
1936-1938 Left JWT to join Donovan, Leisure, Newton & Lumbard (law firm)
1938 Returned to JWT as Assistant Secretary and Head of Legal Department
1942-1943 Assistant Secretary and Assistant Treasure, JWT
1943-1945 Military service during World War II (U.S. Naval Reserve, OSS Middle East and Asia); discharged as Lieutenant
1945 Awarded Legion of Merit, U.S. Army Forces in the Middle East
1946-1960 General Counsel, JWT
1946-1966 Member, Finance Committee, JWT
1949 Awarded Santimala (Peace) Medal from the King of Thailand
1954 Vice President and Trustee of Company Profit Sharing Trust, JWT
1957 Director, JWT
1959 Treasurer and member of Executive Committee, JWT
1961 Senior Vice President, JWT
1962 Succeeded Sam Meek as Executive Vice President (EVP) in charge of international operations
1965 Executive Vice President-Corporate and Secretary of the Company, JWT
1967 Chairman of the Board of Trustees, Earlham College
1971 Director, Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges
1971 Retired from JWT
1976 Honorary Doctorate, Earlham College
1977 Honorary Lifetime Trustee, Earlham College
1987 Presented Distinguished Service Award in Trusteeship by the Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges
1993 July 24 Died in Sharon, Conn.
Collection Overview
The Edward G. Wilson Papers cover the period 1906-1991 and highlight Wilson's 40 year career (1930-1971) as an executive with the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT). The bulk of materials fall between 1946 and 1971, and covers the period from Wilson's return to JWT following military service in World War II until his retirement, and includes Wilson's writings and speeches, clippings, correspondence and memoranda. As General Counsel and head of JWT's Legal Department, Wilson oversaw contractual relations pertaining primarily to the sponsorship of radio and television programs for a number of clients--including DeBeers Consolidated Mines, Ltd., the Eastman Kodak Company, the Ford Motor Company, the Scott Paper Company and Unilever. The collection reveals JWT's relationships with radio and television personalities--such as Fred Allen and Edgar Bergen--and professional organizations like the Radio Writers Guild and the Television Writers of America. In addition, materials in the collection touch on the anti-communist movement and blacklisting within the U.S. entertainment industry of the 1950s--involving personalities such as Jean Muir and John Henry Faulk, among others. The collection also includes records from a number of JWT international offices, with heavier representation from offices in London; Bombay (Mumbai), India; and Johannesburg, South Africa, along with records kept by some of Wilson's predecessors, such as Donald Foote and Sam Meek, and the South African advertising executive and politician James Hamilton Russell.
The papers are organized into twelve series--International Offices (Restricted), Trip Files, Client Files, Chronological Files (Restricted), Legal Files (Restricted), Subject Files, Financial Files (Restricted), Personnel Files (Restricted), Domestic Policy and Procedures, International Policy and Procedures, Writing & Speeches, and Personal Files. The bulk of materials is contained in three large series--International Offices, Chronological Files, and Legal Files. Large-format materials have been located in Oversize Materials. Sensitive personnel materials pertaining to individual employee matters are closed to non-JWT users until 2045, and have been physically removed to Restricted Materials.
The International Offices Series (Restricted) contains files documenting Wilson's tenure as head of JWT's international operations, including information on the England, India and South African offices. The bulk of the records date from the 1950s and 1960s.
The Trip Files Series contains clippings, correspondence, and memoranda detailing trips Wilson made during his tenure as the head of JWT's international operations. Also includes Wilson's reports on the regional offices as well as their clients.
The Client Files Series contains correspondence between Wilson and the managers of individual JWT offices relating to specific clients, such as Caltex, the Campbell Soup Company, S.C. Johnson, Kraft, Pan American Airlines, and the Shell Oil Company and Unilever.
The Chronological Files Series (Restricted) consists of letters and memoranda that reflect the company's routine operations.
The Legal Files Series (Restricted) contains files relating to entertainment law--contract negotiations between the professional unions such as the Radio Writers Guild and the advertisers and agencies; and contractual and billing information pertaining to radio personalities like Fred Allen and Edgar Bergen. Legal actions, disputes, lawsuits, and the blacklisting of entertainers--as well as to corporate affairs, such as stock ownership, profit-shairing, client relations, and lawsuits against JWT are also represented.
The Subject Files Series consist of Wilson's office files and include reports, correspondence, articles and printed materials that cover topics such as Agent-Client relationships, employee evaluations and recruitment, management meetings, and client records, especially for the Eastman Kodak Company, the Ford Motor Company and the Scott Paper Company.
The Financial Files Series (Restricted) include Finance Committee minutes and background materials, along with organizational information on regional offices.
The Personnel Files Series (Restricted) consists of statistical records of departmental personnel, as well as biographical information, clippings, and correspondence relating to transfers, promotions, and job responsibilities of individual executives and office managers.
The Domestic Policies and Procedures Series and International Policies and Procedures Series document the operational guidelines for JWT's domestic and international offices.
The Writing and Speeches Series contains primarily speeches given by Wilson, including several made after his retirement.
The Personal Files Series includes correspondence, interviews and articles about Wilson that reflect in large part Wilson's ongoing relationship with JWT after his retirement.
Related Material
Related materials may be found in other collections within the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives--including the Corporation Vertical Files, Account Files Collection, Information Center Records, and Review Board Records, along with the papers of JWT executives--the George Black Papers, the Harry Clark Papers, the Denis Lanigan Papers, the Samuel Meek Papers, the Dan Seymour Papers, the Albert Stridsberg Papers, the Norman Strouse Papers, and the James Webb Young Papers. For materials relating to JWT's international operations, see also the Shirley Woodell Papers, the Greg Bathon Papers, and the Don Johnston Papers. For materials relating to the legal aspects of advertising, see the American Association of Advertising Agencies Records and the McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center Collection. For additional information on television advertising within the J. Walter Thompson Company, see the John Devine Papers and the Maury Holland Papers.
Advertising agencies -- Law and legislation; Advertising agencies -- South Africa; Advertising -- Management; Advertising executives; Radio Writers Guild; International business enterprises -- Management; Blacklisting of entertainers -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Television Writers of America; Clippings (information artifacts); Writings; Speeches; Memoranda; Television programs -- United States; Radio programs -- United States; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- Great Britain; Advertising agencies -- India; Bergen, Edgar, 1903-1978; Allen, Fred, 1894-1956; Wilson, Edward G., 1909-1993; Scott Paper Company; Unilever (Firm); Muir, Jean, 1911-; De Beers Consolidated Mines; Russell, James Hamilton; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Meek, Samuel W. (Samuel Williams), 1895-; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Johannesburg Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office; Ford Motor Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Mumbai Office; Faulk, John Henry; Foote, Donald C.; Eastman Kodak Company
- International Offices Series, 1933-1971, bulk 1950s-1960s (RESTRICTED), 19 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains files documenting Wilson's tenure as head of JWT's international operations, including information on the England, India, and South Africa offices (dating back to the 1930s). The England files include account planning and review boards. Also includes files from Australia, Brazil, Canada, etc., offices that include the files of Sam Meek, Wilson's predecessor. The South Africa records include those created by Donald Foote and James Hamilton Russell, in particular, correspondence and printed material related to the latter's anti-apartheid political efforts during the 1950s-1960s. Arranged in alphabetical order by name of country in which the office is located.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Sensitive personnel materials pertaining to individual employee matters are closed to non-JWT users until 2045. Those items have been physically removed to Restricted Materials. A note indicating the removal of restricted materials appears at each relevant folder.
  - Australia (Box 1)
    - General
      - Deferred compensation plan, 1950-1951, 1960-1962 (Restricted materials removed), 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Deferred compensation plan, Ted Jarvis, 1960-1961 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 1)
    - Office: Brisbane
      - Correspondence, 1961 May - 1961 Aug. (Restricted materials removed) (Box 1)
    - Office: Melbourne
      - Correspondence (Sam Meek's files), 1957-1961 (Restricted materials removed), 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Office: Sidney
      - Office space, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - Austria
    - Office: Vienna
      - Correspondence, 1960-1966 (Restricted materials removed), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Belgium
    - Office: Antwerp
      - Correspondence, 1952-1967 (Restricted materials removed), 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Salaries, 1965 Jan.-Apr. (Restricted materials removed) (Box 1)
  - Brazil
    - General
      - Association with Maguary, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
    - Office: Rio de Janeiro
      - Correspondence, 1955-1962 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 1)
    - Office: São Paulo
      - Correspondence
        - Assorted
          - 1961-1962 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 1)
          - 1969-1971 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 2)
        - Collocated
          - Vol. I, 1961-1962 (Restricted materials removed), 2 folders (Box 2)
          - Vol. II, 1962-1967 (Restricted materials removed), 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Sam Meek's files, 1945-1961 (Restricted materials removed), 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Office space, 1961-1966 (Box 2)
  - Canada
    - Office: Montreal
      - Background information, 1965 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Sam Meek's files), 1954-1959
        - 1954-1959 (Box 2)
        - 1960-1963 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 3)
    - Office: Vancouver
      - Correspondence, 1956-1965 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 3)
  - Chile
    - Office: Santiago
      - Background information, 1963 Oct. (Restricted materials removed) (Box 3)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1960-1965 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 3)
        - Sam Meek's files, 1943-1961 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 3)
  - Colombia
    - Office: Bogota
      - Correspondence, 1953-1966 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 3)
      - Report on trip by W. Lee Preschel, 1965 Oct. (Restricted materials removed) (Box 3)
  - Denmark
    - Correspondence, 1955-1966 (Box 3)
  - France
    - Office: Paris
      - Acquisition of another business, 1964-1965 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 3)
      - Correspondence (Sam Meek's files)
        - 1939-1953 (Restricted materials removed), 4 folders (Box 3)
        - 1954-1962 (Restricted materials removed), 11 folders (Box 4)
      - French brochure (Sam Meek's files), 1958-1960 (Box 5)
      - Personnel resignations and problems, 1962-1964 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 5)
      - Reorganization of company, 1962-1967 (Restricted materials removed), 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Germany
    - Office: Frankfurt
      - Correspondence, vol. II, 1963-1967 (Restricted materials removed), 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Office space, 1963 Oct. (Box 5)
      - Pension, profit-sharing, salaries, insurance, 1960-1965 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 5)
  - Great Britain
    - Office: London (See also Oversize Box 89)
      - Articles of Association, 1933-1951 (Box 5)
      - Billing procedure, 1965 Nov. (Box 5)
      - Board meetings, 1968 Feb. (Box 5)
      - British Market Research Bureau, 1965 (Box 5)
      - Corporate documentation, 1933-1966 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence (Box 6)
        - General, 1946-1971 (Restricted materials removed), 5 folders (Box 6)
        - Sam Meek's files, 1948-1958, 5 folders (Box 6)
        - Sam Meek's files, 1959-1962, 5 folders (Box 7)
      - Description of JWT London and British Market Research Bureau, 1957 Dec. (Box 7)
      - Diversification, office administration, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
      - Exchange of stock (London for New York), 1958-1964 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 7)
      - General meetings (Box 8)
        - Vol. I, 1955-1961, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Vol. II, 1961-1969, 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Holidays, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
      - Office space, 1954-1964 (Box 8)
      - Organization, 1959-1965 (See also Oversize Folder 1) (Box 8)
      - Pension plan, 1961-1966 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 8)
      - Personnel selection (Sam Meek's files), 1947 Apr. (Restricted materials removed) (Box 8)
        Discussion of pre-employment testing, with some sample psychological tests and questionnaire guidelines.
      - Public relations for advertising (Lexington International), 1963-1966 (Box 8)
      - Reorganization (Box 9)
        - 1946-1960 (Restricted materials removed), 12 folders (Box 9)
        - 1961-1964 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 10)
      - Research policy, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
      - Review Board, 1965 May (Box 10)
      - Royal Commission on the Press, 1961 (Box 10)
      - Top Hat pensions, 1958 (Box 10)
  - India
    - General (See also Oversize Box 89)
      - Articles of Association and Certificates of Incorporation, 1938-1946 (Box 10)
      - Board of Directors, 1966 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 10)
      - Foreign Exchange Act, 1965-1966, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Indianization, 1965-1967 (Box 10)
      - Indianization and the position of the company
        - 1965-1966, 3 folders (Box 10)
        - 1967-1971, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Outline of a plan for the future, 1966 Oct. (Box 11)
      - Printed materials, 1965 Mar. (Box 11)
      - Restriction on advertising expenditure, 1965-1966, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - Union matters, 1951-1966 (Box 11)
    - Office: Bombay
      - Correspondence
        - Vol. I, 1947-1965 (Restricted materials removed), 3 folders (Box 11)
        - Vol. II, 1966 (Restricted materials removed), Folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 11)
        - Vol. II, 1966 (Restricted materials removed), Folder 3 of 3 (Box 12)
        - Vol. III, 1966-1969 (Restricted materials removed), 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Future of JWT in India, 1961-1962 (Box 12)
      - Krishna Mohan (consultant), 1966 Aug. (Box 12)
  - Ireland (See also Oversize Box 89)
    - Proposed Articles of Association, 1939 (Box 12)
  - Italy
    - Office: Milan
      - Correspondence (Sam Meek's files), 1953-1962, 8 folders (Box 12)
      - David James, 1951-1963 (Restricted materials removed) (Box 13)
      - Report and agenda, 1971 Aug. (Box 13)
  - Japan
    - Office: Tokyo
      - Correspondence, 1963-1966, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Retirement allowance report, 1962-1965 (Box 13)
  - Lebanon
    - Correspondence, 1956-1962 (Box 13)
  - Malaysia and Hong Kong
    - Correspondence, 1955-1966, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Proposals for establishing JWT facilities, 1963 July (Box 13)
  - Mexico
    - Office: Mexico City
      - Correspondence, (Sam Meek's files), 1954-1962, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Netherlands
    - Office: Amsterdam
      - Correspondence
        - 1957-1962 (Box 13)
        - 1963-1967 (Restricted materials removed), 4 folders (Box 14)
      - Office space, 1961-1964 (Box 14)
      - Pension plan, 1963-1965 (Box 14)
  - Panama
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 14)
  - Philippines
    - Office: Manila
      - Correspondence (Sam Meek's files), 1955-1962, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Portugal
    - Correspondence, 1953-1968 (Restricted materials removed), 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Puerto Rico
    - Office: San Juan
      - Correspondence (Sam Meek's files), 1959-1961 (Box 14)
  - South Africa (See also Oversize box 89)
    - General
      - Correspondence
        - Donald Foote's files (Corporation agreement), 1933-1957, 3 folders (Box 14)
        - James Hamilton Russell's files
          - 1957-1961 (Restricted materials removed), 3 folders (Box 14)
          - 1963-1967 (Box 15)
        - Operation of company, 1956-1966, 4 folders (Box 15)
        - Re: agreement, 1955-1971, 3 folders (Box 15)
        - Sam Meek's files, 1943-1962, 3 folders (Box 15)
        - Vol. I, 1942-1956, 2 folders (Box 15)
        - Vol. I, 1957-1964, 2 folders (Box 16)
        - Vol. II, 1965-1971, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Documentary evidence regarding commitments, 1948 (Box 16)
      - Financial statements, 1954-1961 (Box 16)
      - Information on South Africa, 1956 (Box 16)
      - Memorandum of Association, Article of Association, Certificate of Incorporation, 1954 (Box 16)
      - Printed materials, 1969 (Box 16)
      - Printed materials (Caltex), 1955-1962 (Box 16)
      - Printed materials (James Hamilton Russell), 1964-1968 (Box 16)
      - Report, vol. I, 1956
        - Balance sheet (removed from sec. 8), 1954 (Box 16)
        - Early draft, 1956 (Box 16)
        - Final draft, 1956 (Box 16)
        - Sec. II, key correspondence, 1933-1954, Folder 1 of 4 (Box 16)
        - Sec. II, key correspondence, 1933-1954 (Restricted materials removed), Folders 2-4 of 4 (Box 17)
      - Report, vol. II, 1956-1957 (Box 17)
    - Office: Cape Town
      - Correspondence (Donald Foote's files), 1932-1946, 6 folders (Box 17)
      - Correspondence, sale of S.A. business (Donald Foote's files), 1933, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Office: Johannesburg
      - Correspondence (Donald Foote's files), 1932-1934, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Spain (See also Oversize Box 89)
    - Correspondence
      - Vol. I, 1954-1964, Folder 1 of 3 (Box 17)
      - Vol. I, 1954-1964, Folders 2-3 of 3 (Box 18)
      - Vol. II, 1965-1971, 5 folders (Box 18)
  - Sweden
    - Establishment of office, 1965-1967 (Box 18)
  - Switzerland
    - Century Lausanne, 1963-1967, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Establishment of office, 1963-1965, Folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 18)
    - Establishment of office, 1963-1965, Folder 3 of 3 (Box 19)
  - Taiwan
    - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 19)
  - Thailand
    - An Examination of a Company Opportunity, 1969 Aug. (Box 19)
  - Trinidad
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 19)
  - Turkey
    - Correspondence, 1961-1965 (Box 19)
  - Venezuela
    - Office: Caracas
      - Correspondence, 1958-1967, 4 folders (Box 19)
      - Office space, 1962-1963 (Box 19)
  - Zambia
    - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 19)
- Trip Files Series, 1954-1968, 3 boxes
  Contains clippings, correspondence, and memoranda detailing trips Wilson made during his tenure as the head of JWT's international operations. Also includes Wilson's reports on the regional offices as well as their clients. Arranged chronologically and therein by place.
  - 1954 Feb.: Europe (See also Oversize Box 89) (Box 19)
  - 1958 Mar.: Europe (Box 19)
  - 1960 July: Europe (Box 19)
  - 1961 July: Europe (See also Oversize Box 89) (Box 19)
  - 1962
    - Feb.: Europe (Box 19)
    - Mar.: South America (Box 19)
    - May: Europe (Box 20)
    - July: Europe (See also Oversize Box 89) (Box 20)
    - Oct.: Australia, Japan, Philippines (Box 20)
  - 1963
    - Jan.: Europe (See also Oversize Box 89) (Box 20)
    - Apr.: Europe (See also Oversize Box 90) (Box 20)
    - June: Europe (See also Oversize Box 90) (Box 20)
    - July: Detroit and Montreal (Box 20)
    - Aug., Detroit (Ford Dealer Association meetings) (Box 20)
    - Oct.: South America, Washington, D.C., Honolulu, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Nov.: Europe (See also Oversize Box 90) (Box 20)
  - 1964
    - Feb.: Europe (See also Oversize Box 90) (Box 20)